<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2474 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2474.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3168 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3168.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7285 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7285.xml">
]>
<rfc submissionType="IETF" docName="draft-mertus-scone-mowie-for-network-aware-app-latest" category="std" ipr="trust200902">

   <?rfc strict="yes"?>
   <?rfc compact="yes"?>
   <?rfc subcompact="no"?>
   <?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
   <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
   <?rfc text-list-symbols="*o+-"?>
   <?rfc toc="yes"?>
   <front>
      <title>MoWIE for Network Aware Application</title>
      <author initials="Y." surname="Jia" fullname="Yuhang Jia">
         <organization>Tencent</organization>
         <address>
            <postal>
               <street>Flat 9, No. 10 West Building, Xi Bei Wang East Road</street>
               <street>Beijing</street>
               <street>100090</street>
               <street>China</street>
            </postal>
            <email>tonyjia@tencent.com</email>
         </address>
      </author>

      <author initials="Y." surname="Zhang" fullname="Yunfei Zhang">
         <organization>Tencent</organization>
         <address>
            <postal>
               <street>Flat 9, No. 10 West Building,Xi Bei Wang East Road</street>
               <street>Beijing</street>
               <street>100090</street>
               <street>China</street>
            </postal>
            <email>yanniszhang@tencent.com</email>
         </address>
      </author>

      <author initials="Y. R." surname="Yang" fullname="Y. Richard Yang">
         <organization>Yale University</organization>
         <address>
            <postal>
               <street>Watson 208A, 51 Prospect Street</street>
               <street>New Haven,  CT 06511</street>
               <street>United States of America</street>
            </postal>
            <email>yang.r.yang@yale.edu</email>
         </address>
      </author>

      <author initials="G." surname="Li" fullname="Gang Li">
         <organization abbrev="CMRI">China Mobile Research Institute</organization>
         <address>
            <postal>
               <street>No.32, Xuanwumenxi Ave, Xicheng District</street>
               <street>Beijing</street>
               <street>100053</street>
               <street>China</street>
            </postal>
            <email>ligangyf@chinamobile.com</email>
         </address>
      </author>

      <author initials="Y." surname="Lei" fullname="Yixue Lei">
         <organization>Tencent</organization>
         <address>
            <postal>
               <street>Flat 9, No. 10 West Building,Xi Bei Wang East Road</street>
               <street>Beijing</street>
               <street>100090</street>
               <street>China</street>
            </postal>
            <email>yixuelei@tencent.com</email>
         </address>
      </author>

      <author initials="Y." surname="Han" fullname="Yunbo Han">
         <organization>Tencent</organization>
         <address>
            <postal>
               <street>Tencent Building, No. 10000 Shennan Avenue, Nanshan District</street>
               <street>Shenzhen</street>
               <street>518000</street>
               <street>China</street>
            </postal>
            <email>yunbohan@tencent.com</email>
         </address>
      </author>

      <author initials="Sabine" surname="Randriamasy" fullname="S. Randriamasy">
         <organization>Nokia</organization>
         <address>
            <postal>
               <street>Nokia Bell Labs</street>
               <street>Nozay</street>
               <street>United States of America</street>
            </postal>
            <email>sabine.randriamasy@nokia-bell-labs.com</email>
         </address>
      </author>

      <date year="2024" month="March" day="1"/>
      <workgroup>ALTO</workgroup>
      <abstract>
         <t>
      TODO: ADD ABSTRACT ONCE DRAFT IS COMPLETE - BASE OFF OF THE FOLLOWING:

   With the deployment of 5G networks, cloud-based
   interactive services such as cloud gaming have gained substantial
   attention. To ensure users' quality of experience (QoE), a cloud interactive
   service may require not only high bandwidth (e.g., high-resolution
   media transmission) but also low delay (e.g., low latency and low
   lagging).  However, the quality perceived by a user with mobile
   and wireless device may vary, as a function of many factors, and
   unhandled changes can substantially compromise the user's QoE.  In this
   document, we investigate network-aware applications (NAA), which
   realize cloud-based interactive services with improved QoE, by
   efficient utilization of a solution named Mobile and Wireless Information Exposure
   (MoWIE). In particular, this document demonstrates, through
   realistic evaluations, that mobile network information such as MCS
   (Modulation and Coding Scheme) can effectively expose the dynamicity
   of the underlying network and can be made available to applications
   through MoWIE; using such an information, the applications can then
   adapt key control knobs such as media codec schemes, encapsulation, and
   application layer processing to minimize QoE distortion. Based on the
   evaluations, we discuss how the MoWIE features can define extensions of the ALTO protocol,
   to expose more lower-layer and finer grain network dynamics.</t>

      </abstract>
   </front>

   <middle>
      <section title="Current Status of Network-Aware Applications" anchor="sect-1">
         <t>
   With the deployment of 5G networks <xref target="draft-ietf-dmm-5g-uplane-analysis"/>
, an increasing number of
   remote cloud-based
   applications are being deployed (e.g., cloud AR/VR/MR).
   Many conventional interactive, daily business applications are also becoming widely used
   as cloud applications, with the help of mobile networks and cloud, e.g., cloud video
   conference. This shift was further accelerated by the COVID-19 pandemic in 2020, when many people had to stay at home and work/study remotely</t>


         <t>
   To optimize QoE for end users using mobile networks (a.k.a., cellular networks),
   many cloud applications utilize information about the mobile network status, e.g.,
   delay, bandwidth, and jitter, to dynamically balance the generated media
   traffic and the rendering/mixing in the cloud. Currently, such an
   application assumes the network as a link and continuously uses
   client or server measurements to detect network characteristics,
   and then adaptively changes its network-related configuration parameters, possibly impacting QoS handling
   and logical functions supporting the upper layer application.  However, when only application information is
   utilized, the QoE that an application achieves is limited for several reasons.
   First, information from the application side (i.e., the 3rd party application server)
   may have a relatively long delay. When a user
   enters a location with a bad network connectivity, such as an elevator or an underground
   garage, the application will not receive such an information
   immediately.  As a result, the buffer of a video application may run out, resulting in a frozen screen and harming users' QoE. The application also does not have information
   about other users in the cell.  Thus, it cannot know how many
   resources it can get and when this will change.  If other users enter
   the cell and compete for resources, the application layer may misjudge
   the resources available and request a high bitrate.  Then, the delay will
   increase and QoE will again drop. Information from the network layer such as
   physical resource block (PRB) information and utilization rate can
   help applications decide how many resources a user can access in order to inform network quality predictions and  further optimize video streaming. The application, however, cannot get
   this kind of information yet. Because 5G networks deployed by a mobile
   network operation are normally in a different domain than 3rd-party internet-based
   applications, the application server can not directly get the
   network internal status without network exposure. For this reason, there have been continuous
   efforts in 3GPP to increase network exposure.</t>

         <t>
   3GPP mobile networks adhere to standard solutions to get
   dynamic network indicators for use by applications.  In 3GPP, many IP-based QoS mechanisms are used. For example,
   ECN <xref target="RFC3168"/>
 has been
   supported by the 4G radio station (eNB) to provide CE(Congestion
   Encountered) information to the IMS application to perform
   Adaptive Bitrate (ABR) <xref target="TS26.114"/>
. The application can downgrade the
   bit rate after receiving the CE indication, but does not know the exact
   bit rate to be selected. DSCP <xref target="RFC2474"/>
 is used to identify the
   QoS class and paging strategy <xref target="TS23.501"/>
, but typically the application
   cannot dynamically change the DSCP to improve bit rate based on
   network status. Mapping DSCP with 4G QCI or 5G 5QI standards could be a good approach to better realize end-to-end QoS.


   DASH <xref target="MPEGDASH"/>
 is an MPEG standard widely used by
   applications to predict the throughput of the network based on the
   current throughput and buffering state in order to dynamically select a suitable bitrate for the
   next segment of video streaming which
   avoids re-buffering. SAND-DASH <xref target="TS26.247"/>
 defines the mechanism
   through which the network/server can provide available throughput to
   applications; in this case, the better bitrate can be selected by DASH
   application.</t>

<t>
   There is also some early work on network status exposure to TCP servers which may
   also indirectly impact application layer optimization but it does not consider 5G networks <xref target="Sprecher_mobile"/>
,
<xref target="flinck_mobile"/>
   In 5G cellular networks, network capability exposure has been
   specified to allow the 5G system (5GS) to expose user device
   location and network status to 3rd party application servers,
   modeled as AF (Application Function) <xref target="TS23.501"/>
. In such a case, the AF
   can request the 5GS to establish a dedicated QoS Flow to transport an
   IP flow with the AF-provided QoS requirements. Via certain measurements,
   network internal status, including congestion, can be exposed and optimization
   can be carried out for the cellular network <xref target="PBECC"/>
.</t>

<t>
   5G also can
   provide QNC (QoS Notification Control) to an AF if the
   GBR(Guaranteed Bitrate) of the established GBR QoS Flow cannot be
   fulfilled. After receiving the QNC
   notification the AF can change the bitrate, but the AF has no information on which bitrate to
   select. So, 5G enhances the QNC by providing a list of
   AQPs (alternative QoS profiles). With AQP, a 5G network provides
   a subset of supported AQPs with the QNC, and then the AF selects a bit
   rate from 5G network supported AQPs. In such a case, the GBR can
   be fulfilled again if the radio state of the UE is changed.  QoS
   prediction is realized by a network function inside 5GS which collects and
   analyzes the status and qualities of 5G network entities, and
   deliver the analytics results to an entity such as application
   server. </t>

<t>
   However, both network capability exposure and QoS
   prediction solutions are only designed for 5G access and core networks,
   which cannot cover the whole end-to-end network. Enabling applications to detect and understand the various lower layers within 5G networks, particularly the internal DN (data network), is an important area for both industrial and academic researchers. This challenge is addressed by MoWIE.
   </t>

<t>
   MoWIE is a solution that aims
   to realize real-time provisioning of cellular radio network information
   by networks to applications, thus helping service providers achieve better policy control and
   improve user experience. The benefits of the MoWIE concept/solution have been
   experimentally evaluated in several use cases, detailed in Section XXXXX TO EDIT.
</t>

</section>

<section title="MoWIE Architecture and Applications" anchor="sect-2">
   <section title="Architecture of MoWIE" anchor="sect-2-1">
     <t>
      The fundamental idea of MoWIE is to provide on-demand and periodic network information from the network to applications, enhancing policy control and user experience. The architecture comprises three core components: the Client Application, the Mobile Network, and the Application Server. Raw data collected from the Mobile Network is processed and exposed to the Application Server. This server can then request network information and use this information to optimize application functions in the Client Application like bit rate, latency, and jitter. Network information provided by MoWIE includes the following:
      </t>

      <t>
         Cell level Information:</t>

      <t>
      <list style="symbols">
      <t>Number of Downlink PRBs (Physical Resource Blocks) occupied
            during sampling period</t>

      <t>Cell load</t>

      <t>Downlink (DL) MAC data rate per cell</t>

      <t>DL data rate</t>

      <t>Channel status (e.g. RSRP (Reference Signal Received Power) and CQI (Channel Quality Indicator))</t>


      <t>PDCP (Packet Data Convergence Protocol) buffer status</t>

      </list>
      </t>

      <t>
         UE level information (omitting privacy information):</t>

      <t>
      <list style="symbols">
      <t>DL Signal to Inference plus Noise Ratio (SINR)</t>

      <t>Modulation and Coding Scheme (MCS)</t>

      <t>Number of packets occupied in PDCP buffer</t>

      <t>Number of DL PDCP Service Data Unit (SDU) packets</t>

      <t>Number of lost PDCP SDU packets</t>

      <t>Per-UE DL MAC data rate</t>

      <t>Per-UE DL data rate</t>

      <t>Per-UE channel status </t>

      <t>Per-UE PDCP (Packet Data Convergence Protocol) buffer status</t>

      </list>
      </t>
      <t>
         The network information listed here can also be found in 3GPP (PRB <xref target="TS38.211"/>
      , cell load <xref target="TS38.300"/>
         PDCP for 5G <xref target="TS38.323"/>
      RSRP, RSRQ, RSSI <xref target="TS38.331"/>
      , MCS, CQI <xref target="TS38.214"/>
      ,
         The number of packets occupied in PDCP buffer, the number of DL PDCP SDU packets, the number of PDCP SDU packets lost,
         the per-UE PDCP buffer status <xref target="TS38.323"/>
      ),  demonstrate the potential benefits of MoWIE for network-application
         integration over cellular network. Figure 3-1 and Figure 3-2 list the data types corresponding
         to the cell-level information and UE-level information respectively.</t>
      <figure>
      <artwork><![CDATA[
                  +----------------------+--------------------------+
                  |Cell-level Information|     Data type/Range      |
                  +----------------------+--------------------------+
                  |         PRB          |          Uint16          |
                  +----------------------+--------------------------+
                  |         CQI          |          Uint8           |
                  +----------------------+--------------------------+
                  |        RSRP          |          Uint8           |
                  +----------------------+--------------------------+
                  |        RSRQ          |          Uint8           |
                  +----------------------+--------------------------+
                  |     Cell load        |          [0,1]           |
                  +----------------------+--------------------------+
                              Figure 4-1: Cell level data type
      ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <figure>
      <artwork><![CDATA[
                  +------------------------------------+---------------+
                  |         UE-level Information       |Data type/Range|
                  +------------------------------------+---------------+
                  |            Downlink SINR           |     Uint16    |
                  +------------------------------------+---------------+
                  |                MCS                 |     Uint8     |
                  +------------------------------------+---------------+
                  |      Downlink PDCP SDU packets     |     Uint8     |
                  +------------------------------------+---------------+
                  |    PDCP SDU packets lost           |     Uint8     |
                  +------------------------------------+---------------+
                  |    Packets occupied in PDCP buffer |     [0,1]     |
                  +------------------------------------+---------------+
                  |                CQI                 |     Uint8     |
                  +------------------------------------+---------------+
                  |                RSRP                |     Uint8     |
                  +------------------------------------+---------------+
                  |                RSRQ                |     Uint8     |
                  +------------------------------------+---------------+
                              Figure 4-2: UE level data type
      ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

   </section>

   <section title="Standard NAA Use Cases for MoWIE" anchor="sect-2-2">
     <t>
       Cloud gaming, low-delay live shows, and cloud VR are commons NAAs whose QoE can be largely enhanced using MoWIE. These applications require low latency and reliable transmission, interactive features, and high data rates. For instance, cloud gaming demands fast, reliable connections between user devices and cloud servers for motion tracking and visual content delivery, significantly contributing to network traffic. Similarly, low-delay live shows require interactive capabilities with sub-100 ms delays for audience engagement, while cloud VR demands extensive bandwidth and latency as low as 20 ms due to its high data volumes and rendering requirements.
     </t>
     <t>
       Performance requirements across these applications may be characterized by a parameter range. Here we consider 1080p~4K as the resolution range, 60-120 FPS (Frames per second) as the frame rate and H.265 as an example compression algorithm. Given these settings, cloud gaming requires a bandwidth of 20-60 Mbps and latency under 200 ms. For low-delay live shows, 20-50 Mbps bandwidth and latency under 100 ms are needed, while cloud VR demands 100-500 Mbps bandwidth and latency under 50 ms. These values are dependent on the parameter settings and are provided to illustrate the order of magnitude of these parameters for the aforementioned use cases.
     </t>
     <t>
         MoWIE's network information can be used to enhance these applications, particularly in mobile and wireless contexts where existing methods struggle due to indirect or delayed network status measurements. By providing direct, real-time data, MoWIE enables more responsive and effective application adjustments, leading to substantial performance gains and enhanced QoE.
     </t>


   </section>

   <section title="Preliminary Evaluations and Benefits" anchor="sect-2-3">
      <t>
         Preliminary tests demonstrate significant QoE improvements for NAAs using MoWIE. By integrating real-time network information, applications can optimize performance, leading to enhanced QoE and resource savings.
      </t>
     <section title="RAN-assisted TCP optimization" anchor="sect-2-3-1">
       <t>
         In trials on real mobile networks, RAN information was used to inform TCP sending window adjustment by predicting bandwidth and buffer status per-UE at RTT granularity (100 ms) and piggybacking such information in TCP ACK. This approach has shown throughput boosts of up to 100%.
       </t>
     </section>
     <section title="ROI Detection" anchor="sect-2-3-2">

         <t>
            ROI (Region of Interest) detection has been widely studied in recently years as a mechanism to reduce video size and bandwidth consumption by dynamically re-allocating coding schemes for interested and non-interested regions. Current methods utilize application information like application rate and application buffer size as the indicators to roughly adjust the algorithm in interactive video services. However, this information is hard to reflect the real-time network status precisely, making it difficult to balance QoE and bandwidth savings in real-time scenarios, including the standard NAAs outlined above. MoWIE's network information can provide direct, real-time data to improve the performance of ROI methods.
         </t>

         <t>
            Experiments evaluated the following four methods of ROI detection: 1&#41; no ROI detection, 2&#41; rough ROI detection at 10ms delay, 3&#41; accurate ROI detection at 40-70ms delay, and 4&#41; dynamic ROI detection in which bandwidth traces are used to compute transmission delay and inform ROI algorithm adjustments. Network conditions varied from poor (Network 1) to good (Network 2) and fluctuating (Network 3). Our findings show that method 4 provides the best balance between QoE and bandwidth savings, especially in adverse network scenarios.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
              +---+-----------------+-----------------+-----------------+
              |   |    Network 1    |    Network 2    |    Network 3    |
              +---+---+-------------+---+-------------+---+-------------+
              |   |QoE|  BW Saving  |QoE|  BW Saving  |QoE|  BW Saving  |
              +---+---+-------------+---+-------------+---+-------------+
              | 1 |3.8|      0%     |4.8|      0%     |4.3|     0%      |
              +---+---+-------------+---+-------------+---+-------------+
              | 2 |3.8|     5%      |4.8|     9%      |4.3|    7%       |
              +---+---+-------------+---+-------------+---+-------------+
              | 3 |2.2|     2.1%    |4.6|    38%      |3.1|    34%      |
              +---+---+-------------+---+-------------+---+-------------+
              | 4 |3.6|     9%      |4.7|    33%      |4.3|    25%      |
              +---+---+-------------+---+-------------+---+-------------+
              Figure 4-3: QoE and Bandwidth Saving
            ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
       </section>

       <section title="Adaptive Bitrate" anchor="sect-2-3-3">
         <t>
            Many applications such as video live streaming and cloud gaming employ adaptive bitrate (ABR) algorithms to optimize user QoE <xref target="MPC"/>
            <xref target="CS2P"/>. However, traditional ABR algorithms use fixed control rules based on simplified or inaccurate models of the deployment environment, leading to suboptimal performance across a broad set of network conditions and QoE objectives. More recent ABR algorithms, such as Pensieve <xref target="Hongzi"/>, use reinforcement learning to optimize QoE, but still suffer from limitations due to indirect or delayed network status measurements and an incomplete set of network information. MoWIE's network information can be used to enhance ABR algorithms, particularly in challenging network conditions.
         </t>

         <t>
            This experiment applied AI-based rate adaptation utilizing MCS network information from gNBs <xref target="TS38.214"/> in cloud-gaming over Tencent's China Mobile LTE network. MCS information was provided directly to the application. Data was collected over several network conditions: 1&#41; low bandwidth, 2&#41; high user load, 3-5&#41; random user distributions. Lagging rate is defined as the ratio between the number of frames with transmission delay greater than 200ms and the total number of frames.
         </t>
         <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
                        +-------------+--------------------------+
                        |Test Scenario| Reduction of Lagging Rate|
                        +-------------+--------------------------+
                        |     1       |           46%            |
                        +-------------+--------------------------+
                        |     2       |           21%            |
                        +-------------+--------------------------+
                        |     3       |           37%            |
                        +-------------+--------------------------+
                        |     4       |           56%            |
                        +-------------+--------------------------+
                        |     5       |           32%            |
                        +-------------+--------------------------+
                          Figure 4-4: Reduction of Lagging Rate
            ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
         <t>
            We clearly observe a significant reduction in lagging rates across all scenarios.
         </t>
      </section>
   </section>
 </section>

 <section title="On-path Signaling using QUIC" anchor="sect-3">
   <t>
      This section explores a possible implementation of the MoWIE framework using on-path signaling, or inband communication, within the QUIC protocol. We aim to achieve the properties set forth in the charter of the Secure Communication of Network Properties (SCONEPRO) Working Group <xref target="SCONEPRO"/> while being in accordance with signaling design principles recommended in <xref target="RFC9419"/>.
   </t>

   <section title="Technical Framework" anchor="sect-3-1">

      <t>
         Within the Mobile Network, 5G gNBs will regularly collect and process the network information included in the MoWIE framework. The Application Server must then discover the on-path gNB. This may be done by the gNB advertising itself to the Application Server by appending additional QUIC packets to existing connection; possible methods for this are discussed in <xref target="SADCDN"/>. The Application Server can then establish a QUIC connection with the gNB and request network information, both individually and at regular specified intervals. The gNB will then respond with the requested information, which the Application Server can use to optimize the application's behavior.
      </t>

      <t>
         Note that the Application Server initiates the QUIC connection and thus the communication channel is under the application's control and aligns with their networking requirements. Care must be taken during initiation to ensure that the additional QUIC packets can not affect core application functionality. This process should be transparent and respect users privacy, adhering to the principles of minimal information exposure and user consent outlined in <xref target="RFC9419"/>.
         The process should also allow for negotiation of signaling parameters to ensure trust between the Application Server and gNB. The Application Server may leverage QUIC's secure and authenticated transport layer to ensure the integrity and security of the communication.
      </t>

      <t>
         Since the Application Server must pull network information from the gNB, the process is optional. The Application Server can choose to request only the network information desired, only when it is desired. ach additional QUIC connection must be lightweight to assist in scalability. Scalability will ultimately depend on the performance capabilities of gNBs. These additional QUIC connections may strain gNB when under heavy user load.
      </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sect-3-2">
      <t>
         Of key importance in this implementation is the security of the exchanged data. Once authentication between the Application Server and gNB has taken place, any exchanged data must be protected from becoming a vector for possible malicious action. Standard cryptographic techniques should be employed to ensure the confidentiality, integrity, and authenticity of the signaling data. Misuse of this signaling mechanism should be minimized through common security practices such as rate limiting.
      </t>
      <t>
         The initial exposure of the gNB to the Application Server must take place prior to authentication between these two entities. This must be carefully managed to ensure that the gNB is not exposed to any malicious actors.
      </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Benefits and Drawbacks of On-path Signaling" anchor="sect-3-6">
      <t>
         On-path signaling is a powerful tool for enabling real-time network information exchange to enable dynamic NAAs. The primary benefit of an implementation with on-path signaling is that it greatly simplifies the challenge of associating a particular Application Server/Client Application pair with the relevant gNB and as a result, the relevant set of network information.
      </t>
      <t>
         However, on-path signaling also presents several challenges. The mechanism of initial connection outlined above relies on the gNB piggybacking off the existing QUIC connection to advertise itself to the Application Server. To append additional packets on an UDP option or IP header would require support from both the Application Server and Client Application which may be difficult to ensure. The alternative of encapsulating the original payload within a new layer requires the gNB to be able to parse the original, encrypted payload, and may affect, for example, performance of the original core functionality. In both cases we are fighting the encryption and integration protection of the original QUIC connection.
      </t>
      <t>
         Another challenge is the increased overhead associated with maintaining additional QUIC channels. As indicated earlier, in high-traffic scenarios this load may strain gNBs and due to the nature of on-path signaling, the gNB is the only entity that can provide the network information. This may create bottlenecks and limit the scalability of the solution.
      </t>
  </section>
</section>


<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="sect-6">
<t>
   This document has no actions for IANA.</t>

</section>

<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sect-7">
<t>
   The collection, distribution of MoWIE information should consider the
   security requirements on information privacy and information
   integration protection and authentication in both sides.  Since the
   network status is not directly related to any special user, there is
   currently no any privacy issue.  But the information transmitted to
   the application can pass through a lot of middle box and can be
   changed by the man in the middle.  To protect the network
   information, an end to end encryption and integration is needed.
   Also, the network needs to authenticate the information exposure
   provided to right applications.  These security requirements can be
   implemented by the TLS and other security mechanisms.</t>

</section>

<section title="Acknowledgments" anchor="sect-8">
<t>
   The authors would like to thank Huang Wei and Mohamed Boucadair for
   their contribution and technical review comments to the previous versions of this draft.</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references title="Normative References">
	&RFC2474;
	&RFC3168;
    &RFC7285;
</references>
<references title="Informative References">
   <reference anchor="SCONEPRO" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bofreq-joras-scone-protocl-the-topic-formerly-known-as-sadcdn/">
      <front>
          <title>Securing Ancillary Data for Communicating with Devices in the Network</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Joras" fullname="Matt Joras"/>
          <date year="2024" month="February"/>
          <workgroup>SCONEPRO</workgroup>
      </front>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="SADCDN" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-joras-sadcdn-01">
      <front>
          <title>Secure Ancillary Data Communication for CDN Interactions</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Joras" fullname="Matt Joras"/>
          <date year="2023" month="July"/>
          <workgroup>SCONEPRO</workgroup>
      </front>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC9419" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc9419/">
   <front>
       <title>Considerations on Application - Network Collaboration Using Path Signals</title>
       <author><organization>
         T. Hardie, J. Arkko, T. Pauly, M. Kühlewind
       </organization></author>
       <date year="2023" month="July"/>
       <workgroup>SCONEPRO</workgroup>
   </front>
</reference>



<reference anchor="CS2P" target="https://doi.org/10.1145/2934872.2934898">
<front>
<title>CS2P: Improving Video Bitrate Selection and Adaptation with Data-Driven Throughput Prediction</title>
<author>
<organization>Sun, Yi., Yin, Xiaoqi., Jiang, Junchen., Sekar, Vyas., Lin, Fuyuan., Wang, Nanshu., Liu, Tao., and Bruno. Sinopoli</organization>
</author>

<date year="2016"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2934872.2934898"/>
</reference>
<reference anchor="Fahad" target="https://doi.org/10.1109/SITIS.2011.84">
<front>
<title>A Novel Visual Saliency Model for Surveillance Video Compression</title>
<author>
<organization>Fazal Elahi Guraya, Fahad., Alaya Cheikh, Faouzi., and Victor. Medina</organization>
</author>

<date year="2011"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/SITIS.2011.84"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Hongzi" target="https://doi.org/10.1145/3098822.3098843">
<front>
<title>Neural Adaptive Video Streaming with Pensieve</title>
<author>
<organization>Mao, Hongzi., Netravali, Ravi., and Mohammad. Alizadeh</organization>
</author>

<date year="2017"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/3098822.3098843"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="MPC" target="https://doi.org/10.1145/2785956.2787486">
<front>
<title>A Control-Theoretic Approach for Dynamic Adaptive Video Streaming over HTTP</title>
<author>
<organization>Yin, Xiaoqi., Jindal, Abhishek., Sekar, Vyas., and Bruno. Sigopoli</organization>
</author>

<date year="2015"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2785956.2787486"/>
</reference>
<reference anchor="MPEGDASH" target="https://mpeg.chiariglione.org/standards/mpeg-dash">
<front>
<title>ISO/IEC 23009, Dynamic Adaptive Streaming over HTTP</title>
<author>
<organization>ISO/IEC</organization>
</author>

<date year="2020"/>
</front>

</reference>
<reference anchor="Saccadic" target="https://doi.org/10.1037/h0037368">
<front>
<title>Saccadic suppression: A review and an analysis</title>
<author initials="E." surname="Matin" fullname="E. Matin">
</author>

<date year="1974"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1037/h0037368"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Saliency" target="https://doi.org/10.1109/TIP.2009.2030969">
<front>
<title>A Novel Multiresolution Spatiotemporal Saliency Detection Model and Its Applications in Image and Video Compression</title>
<author initials="C." surname="Guo" fullname="C. Guo">
</author>

<author initials="L." surname="Zhang" fullname="L. Zhang">
</author>

<date year="2017"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/TIP.2009.2030969&quot;"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="PQoS_white_paper" target="https://5gaa.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/01/5GAA_White-Paper_Proactive-and-Predictive_v04_8-Jan.-2020-003.pdf">
<front>
<title>Making 5G Proactive and Predictive for the Automotive Industry</title>
<author>
</author>

<date year="2020"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="&quot;" value="5GAA Automotive Association, Tech. Rep.&quot;"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="TS23.501" target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3144">
<front>
<title>3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</title>
<author>
</author>

<date year="2021"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="&quot;System" value="architecture for the 5G System (5GS)&quot;"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="ALTO_METRICS" target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-alto-performance-metrics-09">
<front>
<title>Internet-Draft, draft-ietf-alto-performance-metrics-09</title>
<author>
</author>

<date year="2020"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="&quot;" value="ALTO Performance Cost Metrics&quot;"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="TS26.114" target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=1404">
<front>
<title>3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</title>
<author>
</author>

<date year="2021"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="&quot;IP" value="Multimedia Subsystem (IMS); Multimedia telephony; Media handling and interaction&quot;"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="TS26.247" target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=1444">
<front>
<title>3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</title>
<author>
</author>

<date year="2020"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="&quot;Progressive" value="Download and Dynamic Adaptive Streaming over HTTP(3GP-DASH)&quot;"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="TS38.211" target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3213">
<front>
<title>3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</title>
<author>
</author>

<date year="2017"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="&quot;NR;" value="Physical channels and modulation&quot;"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="TS38.214" target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3216">
<front>
<title>3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</title>
<author>
</author>

<date year="2021"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="&quot;NR;" value="Physical layer procedures for data&quot;"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="TS38.300" target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3191">
<front>
<title>3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</title>
<author>
</author>

<date year="2017"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="&quot;NR;" value="NR and NG-RAN Overall description; Stage-2&quot;"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="TS38.323" target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3196">
<front>
<title>3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</title>
<author>
</author>

<date year="2017"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="&quot;NR;" value="Packet Data Convergence Protocol (PDCP) specification&quot;"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="TS38.331" target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3197">
<front>
<title>3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</title>
<author>
</author>

<date year="2017"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="&quot;NR;" value="Protocol specification&quot;"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="ETSI_MEC" target="https://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_gs/MEC/">
<front>
<title>ETSI GS MEC 012</title>
<author>
</author>

<date year="2019"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="&quot;Multi-access Edge Computing (MEC);" value="Radio Network Information API&quot;"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="ALTO_USE_CASES" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-li-alto-cellular-use-cases">
<front>
<title>Internet-Draft, draft-li-alto-cellular-use-cases-00</title>
<author>
</author>

<date year="2021"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="&quot;" value="Requirements and reference architecture for Mobile Throughput Guidance Exposure&quot;"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Sprecher_mobile" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-sprecher-mobile-tg-exposure-req-arch-03">
<front>
<title>Internet-Draft, draft-sprecher-mobile-tg-exposure-req-arch-03</title>
<author>
</author>

<date year="2017"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="&quot;" value="Mobile Throughput Guidance Inband Signaling Protocol&quot;"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="flinck_mobile" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-flinck-mobile-throughput-guidance-04">
<front>
<title>Internet-Draft, draft-flinck-mobile-throughput-guidance-04</title>
<author>
</author>

<date year="2017"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="&quot;" value="User Plane Protocol and Architectural Analysis on 3GPP 5G System&quot;"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="draft-ietf-dmm-5g-uplane-analysis" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-ietf-dmm-5g-uplane-analysis-04#section-4.1">
<front>
<title>Internet-Draft, draft-ietf-dmm-5g-uplane-analysis-04</title>
<author>
</author>

<date year="2020"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="&quot;" value="ALTO Uses Cases for Cellular Networks&quot;"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="PBECC" target="https://dl.acm.org/doi/pdf/10.1145/3387514.3405880">
<front>
<title>PBE-CC: Congestion control via endpoint-centric, physical-layer bandwidth measurements</title>
<author>
<organization>Xie, Yaxiong, Fan Yi, and Kyle Jamieson</organization>
</author>

<date year="2020"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/3387514.3405880"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="MengZ" target="https://zilimeng.com/papers/zhuge-sigcomm22.pdf">
<front>
<title>Achieving Consistent Low Latency for Wireless Real-Time Communications with the Shortest Control Loop</title>
<author>
<organization>Meng, Z., Guo, Y., Sun, C., Wang, B., Sherry, J., Liu, H. H., Xu, M. (2022)</organization>
</author>

<date year="2022"/>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/3544216.3544225"/>
</reference>

</references>

</back>

</rfc>
	
